Guide to the Records of B. Altman & Co. 1876-1955 (bulk, 1881-1933) MS 31
New-York Historical Society
B. Altman & Co. records
1876-1955 (bulk, 1881-1933)
New-York Historical Society
B. Altman & Co.
MS 31
3.5 Linear feet (2 boxes, 18 volumes)
Employee records, financial records, legal papers, estate material, correspondence, and miscellaneous items of B. Altman & Co. The collection also includes material relating to B. Altman & Co. president Michael Friedsam (president 1931-1931).
Access Restrictions
This collection is stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult it, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased at auction, 1990.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in ten series. Material within each series is filed chronologically.
Series I. President Michael Friedsam, 1915-1933, undated
Series II. Employee Records, 1876-1918
Series III. Financial Records, 1887-1955
Series IV. Legal Records, 1913-1953
Series V. Benjamin Altman Estate Material, 1913-1919
Series VI. Correspondence, 1915-1939, undated
Series VII. Study of Shopping Habits, 1936
Series VIII. Electrical Equipment Inspection Certificates, 1906
Series IX. Publications, 1917, undated
Series X. Medals, 1917
Chronology of B. Altman & Co.
1865 B. Altman & Co. founded by Benjamin Altman as a small dry-goods store at 39 Third Ave., New York City.
c1873 Michael Friedsam, future president, joins B. Altman & Co.
1876 Store moves to 627 Sixth Ave. (at 19th St.); new store known as the "Palace of Trade."
1909 Friedsam becomes Vice President.
1913 Benjamin Altman dies; Friedsam takes over as President of B. Altman & Co. and the Altman Foundation.
1914 Store moves to a twelve-story building on Fifth Ave., between 34th & 35th Streets.
1931 Friedsam dies; John S. Burke succeeds Friedsam as B. Altman & Co. president.
1989 Owner L.J. Hooker Corp. declares bankruptcy; company ceases operations.
(Sources: Encyclopedia of New York; B. Altman & Co.'s Enlarged Store(1914); Joseph Devorkin, Great Merchants of Early New York; Robert Hendrickson, The Grand Emporiums; New York Times.)
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of two boxes and 18 bound volumes, and is organized into ten series. Items are arranged chronologically within each series. The bulk of the material is located in Series I. President Michael Friedsam and Series II. Employee Records, 1876-1917. The Friedsam series contains mostly correspondence, 1915-1918; also news clippings and stock and bond receipts. Other significant series include financial records (bills, receipts, checks, bonds), legal records such as copyright and trademark registrations, and material relating to the estate of Benjamin Altman. The smaller series in this collection contain correspondence, a study of shopping habits, electrical equipment inspection certificates, and medals. The B. Altman & Co. Papers do not include any trade catalogs or company advertisements.
The B. Altman & Co. Papers support research in the fields of New York City business and department store administrative history in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The twelve volumes of employee records may also reveal details useful to genealogists, labor historians, and women's historians, as many include summaries of workers' lives. In addition, the Michael Friedsam material contains correspondence pertaining to philanthropy, art collecting, New York City mayoral politics, and domestic efforts during the first World War.
Bonds (legal records).; Certificates.; Checks (bank checks); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Estate records.; Invitations.; Invoices.; Legal documents.; Medals.; Receipts (financial records); Associations, institutions, etc; Charities; Corporations -- Charitable contributions.; Department stores -- Employees; Department stores -- New York (State) -- New York.; Malicious prosecution -- New York (State) -- New York.; Shopping; Stocks; Altman, Benjamin, 1840-1913; Friedsam, Michael, 1860?-1931
- Series I. President Michael Friedsam, 1915-1933, undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains material relating to B. Altman & Co. President Michael Friedsam (President, 1913-1931), divided into four subseries.
  - Subseries 1. Correspondence, 1915-1918, undated
    Includes material relating to B. Altman & Co., the Altman Foundation, the Fifth Avenue Association, the Fusion Committee of 1917, charitable organizations, and Friedsam's art collection. Also included are letters from jobseekers and letters of introduction, congratulatory and thank you letters, and wedding and funeral invitations.
    - Letters received, 1915-1916 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters received, 1917 Jan.-June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters received, 1917 July-Dec. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters received, 1918 Jan.-June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letters received, 1918 July-Dec. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Letters received, Undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 2. Associations, clubs, and charity material, 1917-1918, undated
    Includes donation lists, meeting minutes, circulars re: luncheon and dinner meetings, and report. Organizations include the Uptown Club (minutes), the Friars club, Merchant's Association, Harmonie Club, and unidentified organizations.
    - Associations, clubs, charity material, 1917-1918, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 3. Stock and bond records, 1921-1933
    Includes records for Friedsam and the Delion Corp.: industrial, bank, mining, oil, public utilities, and railroad stocks and bonds; city and state bonds.
    - Stock and bond records, M. Friedsam/ Delion Corp., 1921-1933 (Offsite-box BA-9, Volume Vol)
  - Subseries 4. News clippings, 1929-1931
    Clippings from New York City newspapers regarding Friedsam, including social events, charity work, the Fifth Avenue Association, and B. Altman & Co.
    - News clippings re: Michael Friedsam, 1929-1931 (Offsite-box BA-10, Volume Vol)
- Series II. Employee Records, 1876-1918
  These volumes contain names of B. Altman & Co. employees; most include dates of employment and residence. Also included in some volumes are remarks on employees by supervisors and references. A number of volumes contain amendments added after the employee left B. Altman & Co. The three index volumes do not correspond to other volumes in this series. These volumes have been numbered for retrieval purposes.
  - Employee Records: name, residence, references, 1876-1894 (Offsite-box BA-1, Volume [1])
  - Employee Records: name, department, residence, dates of employment, references, notes, 1877-1882 (Offsite-box BA-1, Volume [2])
  - Employee Records: name, dates of employment, wages, 1881-1891 (Offsite-box BA-2, Volume [3])
  - Employee Records: name, residence, dates of employment, references, notes, 1885-1896 (Offsite-box BA-2, Volume [4])
  - Employee Records: name, residence, department, dates of employment, references, notes (all employees in this volume hired 1887-1893; some records later amended), 1887-1914 (Offsite-box BA-3, Volume [5])
  - Employee Records: name, position, residence, dates of employment, references, notes, 1894-1899 (Offsite-box BA-4, Volume [6])
  - Employee Records: name, residence, position, dates of employment, references, notes (all employees in this volume hired 1899; some records later amended), 1899-1914 (Offsite-box BA-5, Volume [7])
  - Employee Records: name, department, dates of employment, remarks. Vol. 1: A-K, 1899-1918 (Offsite-box BA-6, Volume [8])
  - Employee Records: name, department, dates of employment, remarks. Vol. 2: L-Z, 1899-1918 (Offsite-box BA-7, Volume [9])
  - Employee Records: Index, 1900-1913 (Offsite-box BA-8, Volume [10])
  - Employee Records: Index, 1903-1917 (Offsite-box BA-8, Volume [11])
  - Employee Records: Index: "Workroom Employees", 1903-1914 (Offsite-box BA-9, Volume [12])
- Series III. Financial Records, 1887-1955
  Includes receipts for items sold at auction, real estate and charity receipts, municipal bills, checks (most signed by Benjamin Altman), bonds, and contribution records.
  - Contribution records. Includes names of contributors and organizations, items donated, donation amount., 1932-1933 (Offsite-box BA-10, Volume Vol)
  - Receipts for fur items sold at auction June 15, 1954; receipts 1955., 1942-1955 (Offsite-box BA-11, Volume Vol)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts, 1909-1916 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts, 1917-1931 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bonds, 1887, 1914-1924 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
  - Checks, 1905-1914 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
- Series IV. Legal Records, 1913-1953
  Includes copyright and trademark certificates of registration and a trial transcript, Weitsman v. B. Altman & Co., case of "malicious prosecution," involving stolen goods.
  - Trial transcript, 1916 (Offsite-box BA-9, Volume Vol)
  - Copyright and trademark Certificates of Registration, 1913-1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
  - Copyright and trademark Certificates of Registration, 1951-1953 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
- Series V. Benjamin Altman Estate Material, 1913 --1919
  Includes B. Altman & Co. stock and bond material; property assessments of the Fifth Ave. store, stables, and other real estate holdings; correspondence regarding execution of Altman's will; surrogate court records; summary of Altman's donation of art to the Metropolitan Museum; material regarding employee life insurance, employee legacies, and the Altman Foundation.
  - Estate material, 1913-1914 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Estate material, 1915-1919 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
- Series VI. Correspondence, 1915 -- 1939, undated
  Letters to John S. Burke re: charitable donations, bonds, social engagements, Arts & Decoration magazine, and other topics. Many concern Michael Friedsam. Other letters received in this series include letters to B. Altman & Co. employees (especially Milton M. Klein), unsigned copies of letters to Washington Times owner Arthur Brisbane, and requests to B. Altman & Co. for charitable contributions.
  - John S. Burke, letters received, 1916-1918 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters received by others, 1915-1939, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
- Series VII. Study of Shopping Habits, 1936
  - "A Study of Shopping Habits and Attitudes Toward Department Stores" prepared for B. Altman & Co., 1936 (Offsite-box BA-10, Volume Vol)
- Series VIII. Electrical Equipment Inspection Certificates, 1906
  From the New York City Dept. of Water Supply, Gas and Electricity's Electrical Bureau and the New York Board of Fire Underwriters.
  - Electrical equipment inspection certificates, 1906 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
- Series IX. Publications, 1917, undated
  - Arts and Decoration magazine (June 1917); "The D.M. Read Co.", 1917; undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
- Series X. Medals, 1917
  Possibly belonging to Michael Friedsam. Commemorating the French and British War Commission, the Imperial Japanese Commission, and the Catskill Aqueduct Celebration.
  - Medals, 1917 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)